<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>politics | Patricio R Estévez-Soto</title>
    <link>/tag/politics/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>politics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu9373bddfa54fa95f4d0bb7fc98cc7983_14930_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>politics</title>
      <link>/tag/politics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crime and COVID-19: Effect of changes in routine activities in Mexico City</title>
      <link>/talk/ucl-mex-alumni-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/ucl-mex-alumni-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mexico: after a year in power, Andrés Manuel López Obrador is failing to contain violence</title>
      <link>/post/after-a-year-in-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/after-a-year-in-power/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When Mexico’s president, Andrés Manuel López Obrador, was sworn into office in December 2018 he promised swift action to stem the bloody crime wave that has ravaged the country &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/27/world/americas/27mexico.html&#34;&gt;in recent years&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with record-shattering homicide counts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/2018/07/31/americas/mexico-homicides-2017-new-numbers/index.html&#34;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/23/mexico-crime-homicides-violence-up-report&#34;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt;, the new government promised drastic reductions in crime. López Obrador, known as AMLO, launched an &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-has-plans-to-make-his-country-safer-but-will-they-work-100441&#34;&gt;ambitious security plan&lt;/a&gt; focused on tackling the “root causes” of crime, ending the war against organised crime and overhauling &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-creates-yet-another-national-police-force-but-it-will-struggle-to-stem-the-bloody-crimewave-107320&#34;&gt;security institutions&lt;/a&gt;, such as the federal police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the number of homicides remain at an all time high and the mishandling of repeated crises suggest that López Obrador’s government is overwhelmed by the deteriorating security situation in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since taking office, the president has repeatedly claimed that homicides &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.latimes.com/world/mexico-americas/la-fg-mexico-homicides-amlo-jorge-ramos-20190412-story.html&#34;&gt;started to drop since he came to power&lt;/a&gt;. But the government’s own data contradicted this. A closer inspection shows that the homicide rate has not decreased over the past year, although it has stopped its vertiginous increase &lt;a href=&#34;https://datos.nexos.com.mx/?p=1067&#34;&gt;for the first time in almost five years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;align-center zoomable&#34;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=1000&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34; srcset=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=429&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=429&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=429&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=539&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=539&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=539&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 2262w&#34; sizes=&#34;(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Homicides in Mexico.&lt;/span&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;attribution&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;license&#34;&gt;Author provided&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the news is hardly a cause for celebration. The current rate – which hovers between 80 and 100 homicides per day – is the highest the country has experienced since current records began in 1997. Sadly, the current lull is no guarantee that homicides will decrease in the future, and they may well increase again – as happened during the presidency of Enrique Peña Nieto between 2012 and 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hugs, not bullets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vowing to end the “war against organised crime”, the president opted for a non-confrontational approach to security, aiming to dissuade offenders and organised criminals through social policy, rather than through policing and criminal justice – a strategy the president summarises as “hugs, not bullets”. In early September, he urged criminals to &lt;a href=&#34;https://mexiconewsdaily.com/news/behave-and-think-of-your-mothers/&#34;&gt;behave and think of their mothers&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has sought to scale back the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/27/world/americas/mexican-militarys-high-kill-rate-raises-human-rights-fears.html&#34;&gt;lethality of its security forces&lt;/a&gt;, but several crises suggest that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/nov/05/mexicos-security-failure-grisly-cartel-shootout-shows-who-holds-the-power&#34;&gt;its light-touch approach is not working&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, 13 state police officers were executed in October by 30 cartel gunmen in an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/oct/15/mexico-police-officers-killed-cartel-ambush-michoacan&#34;&gt;ambush in Aguililla, Michoacán&lt;/a&gt;, a state in western Mexico. In response, the president offered no short-term strategy and instead blamed “social decomposition” in the region, vowing to continue pushing his economic and social policy – which has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/09/world/americas/mexico-minster-urzua.html&#34;&gt;been criticised&lt;/a&gt; for being arbitrary and ill-defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same month, a more damming crisis erupted following the botched capture and subsequent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/oct/18/el-chapo-son-ovidio-guzman-lopez-release-amlo&#34;&gt;release of Ovidio Guzmán&lt;/a&gt;, son of notorious drug trafficker, Joaquín “El Chapo” Guzmán, as cartel gunmen laid siege to Culiacán, capital of Sinaloa state, demanding the release of their leader. The president defended yielding to the cartel’s demands, arguing that not doing so would have led to a bloodbath. But critics &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/analysis/culiacan-shambles-security-plan-mexico/&#34;&gt;widely panned López Obrador&lt;/a&gt; for his government’s mishandling of the Culiacán crisis, noting that it would only embolden other criminal groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_Wv1W0m4eOo&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three women and six children of a Mormon family &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/analysis/how-mexico-small-armies-commit-massacre/&#34;&gt;were then massacred in northern Mexico by a criminal group&lt;/a&gt; in November. As the victims held Mexican and American citizenship, the episode prompted the US president, Donald Trump, to consider designating Mexican criminal groups &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/nov/27/trump-mexico-drug-cartels-terrorists&#34;&gt;as foreign terrorist organisations&lt;/a&gt;, heightening tensions between the two countries. Trump ultimately &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-50697635&#34;&gt;decided against it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;
      Read more:
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mormons-in-mexico-a-brief-history-of-polygamy-cartel-violence-and-faith-126493&#34;&gt;Mormons in Mexico: A brief history of polygamy, cartel violence and faith&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A lack of understanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the root of the government’s failing security policies lie fundamental misunderstandings of Mexico’s criminal phenomenon. Specifically, López Obrador &lt;a href=&#34;https://politica.expansion.mx/presidencia/2019/08/01/amlo-calderon-violencia-organizaciones-lucha-anticorrupcion&#34;&gt;believes&lt;/a&gt; that violence is mainly caused by government security policy and economic strife. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0022002715587053?casa_token=1AJSvveCVkgAAAAA%3AuXN76Lo7Pbvzg-FmFldLgPmv8O_h68wQKX27n3GWBGxKUuTJOm9B497QsjM3NPYJ7HF_6ks6p0KoaRo&#34;&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; that certain security strategies &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/analysis/mexico-president-reprises-controversial-kingpin-strategy/&#34;&gt;can escalate cycles of violence&lt;/a&gt;. But organised crime violence is a deeply complex phenomenon caused by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/nathanielparishflannery/2019/11/22/how-can-mexico-defeat-organized-crime/#7e0ae3cac657&#34;&gt;a wide range of factors&lt;/a&gt; – such as international drug trends, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/69346c82-338c-11e9-bb0c-42459962a812&#34;&gt;competition between and within cartels&lt;/a&gt;, and the embeddedness of organised crime groups in local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way in which the authorities intervene is certainly important, but it is not the only factor causing increases in violence. Furthermore, the absence of violence would not necessarily mean that organised crime groups are defeated, as it could signal a condition known as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/41391931&#34;&gt;“pax mafiosa”&lt;/a&gt;, in which criminal groups rule a territory in relative peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that criminal behaviour is caused by economic strife is a common, though too simplistic view of the problem. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cac.crim.cam.ac.uk/resou/sat&#34;&gt;Research suggests&lt;/a&gt; that criminal behaviour is far more complicated than that, noting that it emerges in certain places and times and not in others due to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-moral-ecology-of-extremism-a-systemic-perspective&#34;&gt;complex interaction&lt;/a&gt; of personal and contextual attributes. Of course, this does not mean that social policies should be abandoned, as they are important to improving welfare in general. But it’s unlikely that they will be enough to turn the tide of criminal violence currently rocking Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the government is to successfully tackle violence related to organised crime in Mexico, it must first take steps to acknowledge the inherent complexity of the problem. Rather than proposing a one-size-fits-all approach, specific policies need to be devised based on a nuanced understanding of the diverse criminal phenomena affecting specific places and their reality.&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation&#39;s page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/126460/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&#34; alt=&#34;The Conversation&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- End of code. If you don&#39;t see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexico-after-a-year-in-power-andres-manuel-lopez-obrador-is-failing-to-contain-violence-126460&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mexico’s new president creates yet another national police force – but it will struggle to stem the bloody crimewave</title>
      <link>/post/new-president-creates-new-police/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-president-creates-new-police/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mexico’s new president, Andrés Manuel López Obrador (known as AMLO), was sworn in on December 1, after a five month transition period following his &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/02/mexico-election-leftist-amlo-set-for-historic-landslide-victory&#34;&gt;landslide electoral victory&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with an unassailable crime wave that has ravaged the country since 2007 – when then-president Felipe Calderón (2006-2012) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/27/world/americas/27mexico.html&#34;&gt;declared an all-out war on organised crime&lt;/a&gt; – López Obrador outlined his security strategy shortly before taking office, after &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-has-plans-to-make-his-country-safer-but-will-they-work-100441&#34;&gt;months of speculation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;3HtKT&#34; class=&#34;tc-infographic-datawrapper&#34; src=&#34;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/3HtKT/1/&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border: none&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Against a background of nearly 30,000 intentional homicides a year (the worst rate in recent history), the plan contains some sensible – though vague – proposals, such as an overhaul of the prison system, and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/marijuana-in-mexico-how-to-legalise-it-effectively-fairly-and-safely-107856&#34;&gt;rethink of drug prohibition&lt;/a&gt;. But his plan has drawn &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/nov/21/president-elect-amlo-pledges-new-military-force-fight-crime-mexico&#34;&gt;intense criticism&lt;/a&gt; for proposing the creation of a new national guard under military control as the main tool to fight crime across the entire country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;
      Read more:
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/marijuana-in-mexico-how-to-legalise-it-effectively-fairly-and-safely-107856&#34;&gt;Marijuana in Mexico: how to legalise it effectively, fairly and safely&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The national guard would combine battalions from the army and navy, as well as the civilian Federal Police, into a new security force under the control of the Ministry of Defence. Furthermore, a recruitment drive aims to grow the fledgling force to 150,000 troops within three years. Though the new force will be nominally under civilian control, its training, discipline, values, hierarchy and daily operations will be under military command. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Boots on the ground&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the campaign, López Obrador promised to send the military back to the barracks. A decade of troops on the frontline of the drug wars has left a string of human rights abuses and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/27/world/americas/mexican-militarys-high-kill-rate-raises-human-rights-fears.html&#34;&gt;piling body count&lt;/a&gt;. So the announcement of a new national guard – which came shortly after the Supreme Court &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jurist.org/news/2018/11/mexico-supreme-court-rules-military-policing-law-unconstitutional/&#34;&gt;struck down&lt;/a&gt; a controversial law that permitted the use of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/as-the-cartels-grow-deadlier-should-the-mexican-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement-89134&#34;&gt;armed forces in policing duties&lt;/a&gt; – left many of his supporters in shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the security plan would in effect dissolve the Federal Police – a civilian agency – and eschews any mention of improving the country’s weak municipal and state police agencies, the national guard is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/es/2018/11/28/opinion-lopez-obrador-guardia-nacional/&#34;&gt;seen by many&lt;/a&gt; as a permanent step towards military control of the security sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was extensively &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ipsnews.net/2018/11/president-elects-security-plan-disappoints-civil-society-mexico&#34;&gt;condemned by Mexican civil society&lt;/a&gt;, as well as by international organisations. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2018/11/mexico-el-plan-del-nuevo-gobierno-debe-enfocarse-en-retirar-las-fuerzas-armadas-de-funciones-de-seguridad-publica/&#34;&gt;Amnesty International&lt;/a&gt; said the proposal “essentially imitates the failed militarised security model [that] has allowed serious human rights violations to be committed by the armed forces”, while &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hrw.org/news/2018/11/16/mexico-military-policing-threatens-rights-0&#34;&gt;Human Rights Watch&lt;/a&gt; called it a “colossal mistake”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/157810194&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;vimeo video&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The trailer for Armed to the Teeth, a film about army brutality in Mexico.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, the proposed force is unlikely to be a panacea. On the one hand, it simply perpetuates the current security strategy that has so far failed to curb violence in the country. On the other, the national guard would still be too small to police a country as large and complex as Mexico, even assuming that it reaches its overly optimistic recruitment targets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The great paradox of police reform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most worrying, however, is that the proposed national guard – the fourth new national police force to be created in as many presidencies – is a perfect example of what &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sup.org/books/title/?id=21512&#34;&gt;Daniel Sabet&lt;/a&gt; called “one of the great paradoxes of police reform in Mexico”. That “seemingly dramatic changes, such as dissolving one police force and creating an entirely new one, might in practice amount to very little reform of how policing is done”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To justify the national guard, López Obrador claims that there have been no improvements whatsoever in the quality of the police services in the past 12 years. This is not precisely true. While most police agencies are far from perfect, there have been notable improvements. The Federal Police has vastly improved its technical and human capabilities since 2006, and several state and municipal forces have become successful &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-43302244&#34;&gt;case&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/09/01/world/americas/mexico-violence-police.html?ref=nyt-es&amp;amp;mcid=nyt-es&amp;amp;subid=article&#34;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt; in their own right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;align-center &#34;&gt;
            &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34; srcset=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=658&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=658&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=658&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=827&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=827&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=827&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 2262w&#34; sizes=&#34;(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px&#34;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Federal Police showcases its air capabilities.&lt;/span&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;attribution&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;source&#34; href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/63/D%C3%ADa_del_Polic%C3%ADa._88_Aniversario_de_la_Polic%C3%ADa_Federal_%2827677338193%29.jpg&#34;&gt;Presidencia de la República Mexicana via Wikimedia Commons [CC BY 2.0]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&#34;license&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that such improvements are sparse and have not yet made a notable improvement in security conditions across the country. Yet this is due to the complex nature of the criminal phenomenon, and the underwhelming commitment to institutional building by incoming politicians, who prefer flashy new policies over sticking to a plan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also true that corruption and abuse persist across police departments. But the armed forces are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/feb/10/mexico-drug-cartels-soldiers-military&#34;&gt;hardly immune to corruption&lt;/a&gt;. Studies have shown that the armed forces are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.animalpolitico.com/blogueros-blog-invitado/2018/11/15/ejercito-y-marina-bajo-la-lupa/&#34;&gt;more prone to commit torture and human rights abuses&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.politicaygobierno.cide.edu/index.php/pyg/article/view/1161&#34;&gt;more lethal&lt;/a&gt; than the police. Thus, it is unlikely that militarisation itself will lead to a more effective, incorruptible police force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remaking the security institutions every time a president takes power is incredibly counterproductive. Creating new institutions is costly and slow. Everything from the legislation (creating the national guard requires &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.proceso.com.mx/560409/morena-propone-modificar-13-articulos-de-la-constitucion-para-crear-la-guardia-nacional&#34;&gt;13 constitutional ammendments&lt;/a&gt; and a score of secondary rules) to the mundane (such as uniforms and the colours of patrol cars) must be defined and approved. This process tends to take much longer than anticipated, wasting resources at the expense of actual police work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better alternative would focus on a long-term commitment to improving Mexico’s fledgling civilian police agencies. Corruption is an inherent risk of all police agencies, yet there is evidence that corrupted police agencies &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.lse.ac.uk/68126/1/Newburn_literature-review%201.pdf&#34;&gt;can be successfully reformed&lt;/a&gt;. By creating a new force, rather than solving Mexico’s security crisis, López Obrador will be setting the country back in its long and arduous road towards capable policing.&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation&#39;s page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/107320/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&#34; alt=&#34;The Conversation&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- End of code. If you don&#39;t see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-creates-yet-another-national-police-force-but-it-will-struggle-to-stem-the-bloody-crimewave-107320&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mexico’s new president has plans to make his country safer – but will they work?</title>
      <link>/post/new-president-has-plans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-president-has-plans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mexican voters upended their country’s political establishment this summer when they elected Andres Manuel López Obrador – the left-wing former mayor of Mexico City known as AMLO – by an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/02/mexico-election-leftist-amlo-set-for-historic-landslide-victory&#34;&gt;overwhelming margin&lt;/a&gt;. His impressive victory owed a lot to his personal charisma and populist rhetoric, but it also reflected the public’s weariness with Mexico’s current state of affairs – and in particular, with criminal violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long a problem for Mexico, deadly violence is now at an all time high. There were &lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/2018/07/31/americas/mexico-homicides-2017-new-numbers/index.html&#34;&gt;more than 31,000 murders in 2017&lt;/a&gt;, the highest number on record, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/23/mexico-crime-homicides-violence-up-report&#34;&gt;this year is shaping up to be even deadlier&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;López Obrador’s term begins on December 1, but his incoming government has already &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AlfonsoDurazo/status/1028131486678044672&#34;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to reduce violent crime by between 30-50% within three years, and to bring crime rates in line with those in OECD countries &lt;a href=&#34;http://uk.businessinsider.com/oecd-homicide-rates-chart-2015-6&#34;&gt;within six years&lt;/a&gt;. To achieve this, it has come up with three strategies: tackling the “root causes” of crime through social policy, ending the war against organised crime, and restructuring security institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the central ideas behind López Obrador’s approach to security is that when it comes to fighting crime, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eleconomista.com.mx/politica/El-reto-es-hallar-las-personas-indicadas-para-hacer-la-tarea-Alfonso-Durazo-20180728-0001.html&#34;&gt;the best policy is social policy&lt;/a&gt;. But muddling social policy with crime policy is troublesome; rather than lifting people out of criminogenic conditions, it can simply spawn a welter of social programmes that have little bearing on crime at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what happened during the tenure of the outgoing administration, when every proposal from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cidob.org/en/articulos/revista_cidob_d_afers_internacionals/116/the_effects_of_prevention_of_crime_and_violence_policy_in_mexico&#34;&gt;cooking lessons to handing out free glasses to schoolchildren&lt;/a&gt; was held up as a worthwhile crime prevention initiative. This sort of policymaking neglects the fact that the police can actually be &lt;a href=&#34;http://whatworks.college.police.uk/toolkit/Pages/Toolkit.aspx&#34;&gt;very effective at preventing crime&lt;/a&gt; in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMLO clearly sees things differently. He plans to roll out an extensive scholarship programme aimed at preventing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://verne.elpais.com/verne/2018/02/02/mexico/1517594700_019834.html&#34;&gt;7m young people not in education, employment or training&lt;/a&gt; from joining criminal gangs, even though there is no consistent evidence showing that youth unemployment and poverty are the main drivers of involvement in organised crime. Though scant research on this topic has been conducted in Mexico itself, evidence from the UK has shown the opposite: as youth unemployment and poverty has increased, the amount of crime committed by this age group has actually &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/is-there-a-link-between-youth-poverty-and-crime-the-answers-may-surprise-you-50097&#34;&gt;decreased&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Beyond the drug war&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a different front, the incoming government has correctly identified the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/dec/26/mexico-maelstrom-how-the-drug-violence-got-so-bad&#34;&gt;decade-long war on organised crime&lt;/a&gt; as one of the main drivers of violence. But while it has proposed a three-pronged plan to bring about peace, it is unlikely that this is achievable in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, AMLO and his team have proposed implementing a process of transitional justice to break the cycle of violence, including a controversial &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/amnesty-for-drug-traffickers-thats-one-mexican-presidential-candidates-pitch-to-voters-96063&#34;&gt;amnesty for low-level drug-traffickers&lt;/a&gt;. There is still much uncertainty as to how this would be implemented, but it remains unclear whether it would actually help end violence in Mexico, since these mechanisms were designed to manage the aftermath of political and ethnic conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, with a growing global consensus that the current &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/apr/02/un-war-on-drugs-failure-prohibition-united-nations&#34;&gt;drug prohibition regime has failed&lt;/a&gt;, the new government plans to legalise cannabis and the cultivation of opium poppies. However, wholesale legalisation of cannabis has never been attempted in a country as large and complex – and as fraught with poor institutions – as Mexico. That means it may be years before legalisation is implemented, as the necessary regulatory frameworks and institutions will have to be established first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, legalisation in Mexico would create more opportunities for smuggling drugs into the US – potentially a boon for some organised crime groups, and potentially a serious risk to an already troubled relationship with Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the new government has pledged to train enough police officers to &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/as-the-cartels-grow-deadlier-should-the-mexican-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement-89134&#34;&gt;remove the armed forces&lt;/a&gt; from the fight against organised crime in three years. But this plan is based on a highly optimistic estimate of the state’s capacity to recruit and train new police officers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 2015 and 2016, there were &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vox.com/2018/8/15/17690420/mexico-president-amlo-drug-war-cartels-violence-legalization&#34;&gt;133,000 soldiers involved in the fight against organised crime&lt;/a&gt;; replacing them would require at least 50,000 new elite federal police officers. President Calderón (2006-2012) took six years to recruit 20,000 federal police officers. His successor, Peña Nieto, promised a 50,000-strong National Gendarmerie, but ultimately delivered a force of fewer than 5,000. It’s highly unlikely that the new government will be able to perform any better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reinventing the police&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incoming government has also hinted at yet another redesign of Mexico’s security institutions. Though they have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.animalpolitico.com/2018/07/guardia-nacional-amlo-seguridad/&#34;&gt;dropped a plan&lt;/a&gt; to create a “National Guard” incorporating the army and the police, AMLO plans to recreate the Federal Security Ministry (dissolved by the outgoing president, Enrique Peña Nieto), to form a new police force charged with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2018-07-13/amlo-s-top-cop-no-longer-sees-new-border-police-force-in-mexico&#34;&gt;protecting tourist destinations&lt;/a&gt;, and to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cfr.org/blog/coming-us-mexico-blow&#34;&gt;replace the country’s intelligence agency&lt;/a&gt; with an entirely new body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These reforms are likely to take much longer than anticipated, wasting precious resources that could otherwise be spent on actual police work. And even if they’re implemented swiftly, they are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/analysis/mexico-needlessly-plans-to-alter-justice-agency/&#34;&gt;unlikely to directly improve the security situation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mexico is simply too vast and too diverse for centralised control of security policy to work. The federal government does not and will not have the resources to properly deal with most of its crime problems. A better approach would be to delegate responsibility to state and local governments, using federal policy to induce improvements in local policing. Security institutions require continuity and time to mature; small, incremental improvements to their operations are a better bet than wholesale redesign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The security situation in Mexico remains dire, and it’s likely to remain that way for some time. Social policy can help reduce poverty and improve welfare, but it’s no substitute for intelligent, evidence-based crime prevention delivered by a well-trained local police. Removing the army from the streets without capable police officers to replace them could strengthen organised crime groups and make the situation worse.&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation&#39;s page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/100441/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&#34; alt=&#34;The Conversation&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- End of code. If you don&#39;t see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-has-plans-to-make-his-country-safer-but-will-they-work-100441&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>As the cartels grow deadlier, should the Mexican military be involved in law enforcement?</title>
      <link>/post/should-the-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/should-the-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement/</guid>
      <description>  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/199203/original/file-20171214-27593-10frerr.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;figcaption&gt;
        Boots on the ground.
        &lt;span class=&#34;attribution&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;source&#34; href=&#34;https://www.shutterstock.com/download/confirm/609862967?src=D_gW8H_zgs3FQHVU8cTjyQ-1-0&amp;size=medium_jpg&#34;&gt;Shutterstock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the main mission of the Mexican Armed Forces (army, air force and navy) is to safeguard national security, Mexico is faced with very few direct foreign threats. Consequently, the armed forces instead focus most of their attention on internal threats: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/live/2017/sep/21/mexico-earthquake-search-for-survivors-live-frida-sofia-updates&#34;&gt;emergency response to natural disasters&lt;/a&gt;, and temporary operations for countering organised crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successive Mexican presidents have continuously relied on the well-armed and highly respected armed forces to combat the large and powerful organised crime groups (colloquially known as “cartels”) that dominate the Latin American drug trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have done it for two reasons. On the one hand, local and state police forces have been neglected for decades and have been unable to cope with the corruptive influence of criminal groups. On the other, federal police forces have been too weak and small to counter the national presence of powerful cartels. So when faced with a rising death toll and increasingly violent organised crime groups, presidents have had few alternatives but to turn to the military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-react-class=&#34;Tweet&#34; data-react-props=&#34;{&amp;quot;tweetId&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;940656527685271552&amp;quot;}&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until a decade ago, these interventions were rather sporadic. The most dramatic upsurge came about in 2006, when then-president Felipe Calderón (2006-2012) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/27/world/americas/27mexico.html&#34;&gt;declared an all-out war on organised crime&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the decade-long strategy was successful in breaking apart the main organised crime groups, violence induced by splinter groups and new actors has not abated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strategy has plunged the country into an ongoing conflict that has cost thousands of lives. Furthermore, it has also provoked countless human rights violations by the security forces (including the military) in the form of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/campaigns/2015/10/stop-torture-mexico/&#34;&gt;torture&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=20143&#34;&gt;extrajudicial killings&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hrw.org/news/2013/02/20/mexico-crisis-enforced-disappearances&#34;&gt;forced disappearances&lt;/a&gt;, and has led to an explosion in criminality in both &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.animalpolitico.com/2012/10/aumenta-delincuencia-comun/&#34;&gt;petty&lt;/a&gt; and serious crime, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/the_americas/kidnappings-in-mexico-surge-to-the-highest-number-on-record/2014/08/15/3f8ee2d2-1e6e-11e4-82f9-2cd6fa8da5c4_story.html?utm_term=.c2a58b74639e&#34;&gt;kidnapping&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.huffingtonpost.com/fundacion-mepi/extortion-by-fire-more-me_b_3202869.html&#34;&gt;extortion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;QJnd8&#34; class=&#34;tc-infographic-datawrapper&#34; src=&#34;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/QJnd8/1/&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border: none&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Peña Nieto (in office since 2012) has sought to scale back the focus of the Calderón government’s war on organised crime. This led to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/news/special-report/21566774-after-five-years-soaring-murder-rates-killings-have-last-begun-level&#34;&gt;an illusory lull in homicide trends&lt;/a&gt; for the first couple of years of his term, only for violence to return with a vengeance: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/entry/mexico-october-deadliest-month_us_5a158a7ee4b09650540e9189&#34;&gt;October 2017 was Mexico’s deadliest month on record&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the tenth anniversary of the war on organised crime, Mexico’s secretary of defence &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eluniversal.com.mx/articulo/nacion/seguridad/2016/12/5/cienfuegos-no-confundir-seguridad-interior-con-seguridad-publica&#34;&gt;complained&lt;/a&gt; about the lack of a proper legal framework for the involvement of the armed forces in “matters of internal security”, including the fight against organised crime. Such criticism was echoing a 2012 statement by a minister of the Supreme Court, who &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.animalpolitico.com/2012/08/el-ejercito-no-esta-para-cumplir-funciones-de-seguridad-publica-cossio-integro/&#34;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; that the constitution did not empower the army to take on roles attributed to civil law enforcement agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Internal Security Law&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fill this legal vacuum, legislators proposed an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.senado.gob.mx/sgsp/gaceta/63/3/2017-12-05-1/assets/documentos/Minuta_Ley_Seguridad_Interior.pdf&#34;&gt;Internal Security Law&lt;/a&gt;, approved on November 30 by the Chamber of Deputies (Mexico’s lower house of congress), with support from the governing PRI party and a few PAN deputies (the largest opposition party). The bill set to now be debated (and probably approved) by the Senate seeks to regulate the involvement of the armed forces in “threats to internal security”. Such interventions would have to be requested by state governments, or could be initiated by the president if the threats are deemed to be urgent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;align-center &#34;&gt;
            &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34; srcset=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=398&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=398&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=398&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=501&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=501&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=501&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 2262w&#34; sizes=&#34;(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px&#34;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The police are struggling to contain a wave of violent crime.&lt;/span&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;attribution&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;source&#34; href=&#34;https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/veracruz-mexico-january-192015antidrug-special-foreces-336562550?src=D_gW8H_zgs3FQHVU8cTjyQ-1-2&#34;&gt;Shutterstock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proponents of the law note that such “actions of internal security” are never supposed to substitute local law enforcement; are bound to respect human rights; are to be deployed only against specific threats for a limited time (though subject to extensions); are explicitly forbidden to be used against peaceful social and political protests; and should involve the military only if the Federal Police cannot deal with the threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the proposed law has been met with wide opposition from civil society organisations, academics, and international organisations such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=22492&amp;amp;LangID=E&#34;&gt;United Nations Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hrw.org/news/2017/12/07/mexico-reject-internal-security-law&#34;&gt;Human Rights Watch&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://amnistia.org.mx/contenido/declaracion-ai-ley-de-seguridad-interior/&#34;&gt;Amnesty International&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics claim that given the country’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/nov/07/mexican-military-human-rights-abuses-war-on-drugs-report&#34;&gt;poor track record&lt;/a&gt; in punishing human rights abuses by the military, institutionalising their role in law enforcement could lead to more abuse. Furthermore, they argue that the vague definition of “threats to internal security” gives too much discretion to the president, prompting fears that the military might be deployed as a tool of political repression. They also complain that the law rolls back accountability and transparency, as all information related to such interventions would be automatically classified as state secrets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It’s about trust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that there is a legal void regarding the involvement of the armed forces in internal threats. Such participation of the military in civilian life is not exclusive to Mexico. Liberal democracies increasingly resort to the military &lt;a href=&#34;http://euromil.org/the-use-of-military-forces-for-internal-security-tasks/&#34;&gt;in support of internal security missions&lt;/a&gt;, including in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-16195861&#34;&gt;the UK&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/apr/15/paris-attacks-operation-sentinelle-soldiers-patrolling-streets-france-safer&#34;&gt;France&lt;/a&gt;, for example. The question is how, and to what extent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed law does attempt to regulate such involvement in principle, however it does little more than state in law what already takes place in practice. Not surprisingly, this raises legitimate fears that it will only lead to a perpetuation of the status quo at the expense of developing capable local civil law enforcement institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A truly beneficial law on internal security, if any, would go to greater lengths to curb the executive’s use of the armed forces to deal with internal security problems, for example by mandating stricter mechanisms for oversight (including legislative and judicial control) and by defaulting the interventions at their most restrictive setting, rather than leaving their terms to executive discretion.&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation&#39;s page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/89134/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&#34; alt=&#34;The Conversation&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- End of code. If you don&#39;t see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/as-the-cartels-grow-deadlier-should-the-mexican-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement-89134&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
