<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mexico | Patricio R Estévez-Soto</title>
    <link>/tag/mexico/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/mexico/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Mexico</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu9373bddfa54fa95f4d0bb7fc98cc7983_14930_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Mexico</title>
      <link>/tag/mexico/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of the kingpin strategy on extortion and kidnapping in Mexico</title>
      <link>/talk/24h-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/24h-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on personal victimisation</title>
      <link>/talk/covid-19-mx-victim-ecca-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/covid-19-mx-victim-ecca-2022/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>¿Cómo pueden los análisis cuantitativos ayudar a prevenir el delito?</title>
      <link>/talk/foro-rno-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/foro-rno-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crime and COVID-19: Effect of changes in routine activities in Mexico City</title>
      <link>/publication/estevez-soto-2021-crime-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/estevez-soto-2021-crime-science/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving the measurement of extortion victimisation: The case of Mexico</title>
      <link>/talk/gsj-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 17:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/gsj-2021/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/P9wXN-DqXDY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crime and COVID-19: Effect of changes in routine activities in Mexico City</title>
      <link>/talk/ucl-mex-alumni-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/ucl-mex-alumni-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>¿Por qué algunas empresas pagan extorsión y otras no?</title>
      <link>/talk/extorsion-gi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/extorsion-gi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Determinants of extortion compliance: Empirical evidence from a victimisation survey</title>
      <link>/publication/estevez-soto-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/estevez-soto-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crime and COVID-19: Effect of changes in routine activities in Mexico City</title>
      <link>/talk/covid-19-mx/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 14:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/covid-19-mx/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    The seminar is free and open to all, so &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/covid-crime-research-seminar-tickets-126515799161&#34;&gt;register now&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-research-seminar-flyer&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/covid-seminar-flyer.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Research seminar flyer.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/covid-seminar-flyer.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Research seminar flyer.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Register Now: COVID-19 and Crime Research Seminar</title>
      <link>/post/covid-19-mx-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 18:32:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/covid-19-mx-talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m thrilled to have been invited by &lt;a href=&#34;https://essl.leeds.ac.uk/law/staff/193/professor-graham-farrell&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Professor Graham Farrell&lt;/a&gt; to speak at a research seminar showcasing recent work on the impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on crime and policing. The seminar is organised as part of an UKRI ESRC grant focused on &lt;a href=&#34;https://covid19-crime.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Reducing the Crime Harms of the COVID-19 Pandemic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be &lt;a href=&#34;/talk/covid-19-mx/&#34;&gt;presenting&lt;/a&gt; my research on the effects of the &lt;a href=&#34;/publication/estevez-soto-2020-covid/&#34;&gt;COVID-19 pandemic on crime patterns in Mexico City&lt;/a&gt;, though there are other fantastic speakers presenting their research. The speakers and papers that will be presented are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shane Johnson, Manja Nikolovska &amp;amp; Paul Ekblom. &lt;em&gt;Policing, disruption and mobilisation through Twitter. An analysis of UK law enforcement tweeting practices during the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nick Tilley, Lara Adamson &amp;amp; Anthony Dixon. &lt;em&gt;COVID-19 and Crime: Change and Continuity on the Railway.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Samuel Langton, Anthony Dixon &amp;amp; Graham Farrell. &lt;em&gt;Six Months In: Pandemic Crime Trends in England and Wales to August 2020.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anthony Dixon, Manne Gerell &amp;amp; Graham Farrell. &lt;em&gt;Crime during the pandemic. A cross-national comparison between Sweden and England &amp;amp; Wales.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patricio R Estévez-Soto. &lt;em&gt;Crime and COVID-19: Effect of changes in routine activities in Mexico City&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matt Ashby. &lt;em&gt;Changes in police calls for service during the early months of the 2020 coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The seminar is free and open to all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Wednesday December 9, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 14:00-16:00 GMT (London)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location:&lt;/strong&gt; Online, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/covid-crime-research-seminar-tickets-126515799161&#34;&gt;register now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;








  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-research-seminar-flyer&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/media/covid-seminar-flyer.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Research seminar flyer.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/media/covid-seminar-flyer.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Research seminar flyer.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crime and COVID-19: Effect of changes in routine activities in Mexico City</title>
      <link>/publication/estevez-soto-2020-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 16:15:03 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/estevez-soto-2020-covid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crime and Covid-19</title>
      <link>/project/crime-and-covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 22:53:22 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/crime-and-covid-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This study seeks to examine the effect of the covid-19-related changes in routine activities on crime patterns in an urban area. Using data from Mexico City, I will first identify a suitable proxy measure to estimate the amount of activity outside homes (such as public transit passenger numbers, mobility apps trip queries, or amount of air pollution) before and after the social distancing restrictions imposed due to the Covid-19 epidemic. Then, I will examine if spatio-temporal crime patterns are associated with those of the proxy measures of routine activities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crime and Covid-19: Effect of changes in routine activities in Mexico City</title>
      <link>/post/crime-and-covid-19/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/crime-and-covid-19/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ucl.ac.uk/coronavirus/&#34;&gt;Covid-19 pandemic&lt;/a&gt; has thus far infected 5.6 million people and caused an excess of 350 thousand deaths worldwide. Latin America and the Caribbean are particularly likely to be affected by this crisis. On the one hand, the World Health Organisation said that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/may/27/global-report-who-says-the-americas-are-centre-of-pandemic-as-cases-surge&#34;&gt;Americas have become the new centre of the pandemic&lt;/a&gt;, as cases and deaths have surged in the region, overtaking daily infections in Europe and the United States. In addition, the pandemic is also likely to wreak havoc in the economy and stability of LAC countries. The United Nations&#39; Economic Commission for Latin America and the Caribbean (ECLAC) estimates that the pandemic &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.un.org/en/story/2020/04/1062292&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;will cause the greatest economic contraction ever&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in Latin America and the Caribbean, causing unemployment to rise to 38 million in the LAC region, and poverty to increase by 4.5 percentage points. It is estimated that the pandemic will drive 30 million people into poverty across the LAC region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style=&#34;width: 100%; height: 800px; border: 0px none;&#34; src=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus-data-explorer?yScale=log&amp;amp;zoomToSelection=true&amp;amp;country=CAN~BRA~ARG~BOL~CHL~COL~ECU~PER~MEX~GTM~CRI~PAN~PRY~JAM&amp;amp;deathsMetric=true&amp;amp;dailyFreq=true&amp;amp;aligned=true&amp;amp;smoothing=7&#34;&gt;&lt;span data-mce-type=&#34;bookmark&#34; style=&#34;display: inline-block; width: 0px; overflow: hidden; line-height: 0;&#34; class=&#34;mce_SELRES_start&#34;&gt;﻿&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The devastating effects of the pandemic across the economy and society are likely to have long term consequences on crime and security across the LAC region. While there has been &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/analysis/coronavirus-organized-crime-latin-america/&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.brookings.edu/on-the-record/covid-19-and-organized-crime-latin-american-governments-are-in-a-state-making-competition-with-crime/&#34;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; on the potential effects of covid-19 on criminal governance, illicit markets, and the strength of organised crime, there has thus far been little discussion of the short term effects on crime patterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most visible effects of the pandemic on daily life has been a drastic and sudden reduction in personal mobility across the world. As reducing person-to-person contact is one of the most effective means to slow the transmission of the disease, by April 3rd, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.euronews.com/2020/04/02/coronavirus-in-europe-spain-s-death-toll-hits-10-000-after-record-950-new-deaths-in-24-hou&#34;&gt;around 3.9 billion people&lt;/a&gt;─around half of the world&amp;rsquo;s population─had been under covid-19 related lockdowns. Though &lt;a href=&#34;https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2020/03/mexico-is-frighteningly-unprepared-for-the-coronavirus.html&#34;&gt;Mexico was slow to enact covid-19 lockdowns&lt;/a&gt;, and even allowed massive concerts in Mexico City to go ahead during the early days of the pandemic, the government issued a nationwide lockdown in March 23. While in Mexico City &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.csmonitor.com/World/2020/0420/If-you-don-t-work-you-don-t-eat-Where-lockdowns-have-extra-sting&#34;&gt;many people have continued to work in public places defying the lockdown&lt;/a&gt;, data released by the city&amp;rsquo;s mobility secretary suggests a substantial decline in overall mobility. For example, the tweet embedded below shows the reduction in mobility by comparing trips between bike-sharing stations in early March vs late April. Data on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/andreslajous/status/1255483772973309953?s=20&#34;&gt;volume of vehicular traffic&lt;/a&gt; suggests a similar decline consistent with the covid-19 lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;es&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Estas dos imágenes muestran los viajes entre estaciones de Ecobici. La primera imagen es de la semana del 2 de marzo del 2020, y la segunda imagen es de la semana del 20 de abril del 2020. Las imágenes dan la sensación de que al bajar la movilidad las cosas se apagan. &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/xDFbYPA1fm&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/xDFbYPA1fm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrés Lajous (@andreslajous) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/andreslajous/status/1255488426675183616?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;April 29, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/coronavirus-how-crime-changes-during-a-lockdown-134948&#34;&gt;It is very likely that such drastic reductions in mobility could have substantive effects in the incidence of crime during the lockdown&lt;/a&gt;. This is because the patterns of crime we typically observe in a city don&amp;rsquo;t happen in a vacuum. Instead, they are a function of a city&amp;rsquo;s routine activities and rhythms of daily life (work, school, leisure, etc.), as these determine the rate at which criminal opportunities occur (i.e., how often  a motivated offender and a suitable target converge in the absence of a capable guardian). As Lawrence Cohen and Marcus Felson identified in their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2094589?seq=1&#34;&gt;seminal paper&lt;/a&gt;, when changes in routine activities affect the rate at which such criminal opportunities occur, it is likely that the incidence of crime will change. In the case of the covid-19 lockdown, this would suggest that crimes that take place in public (such as street robbery) would likely see reductions (because there are fewer people on the streets), while crimes that take place in private (such as domestic violence) may increase (as people are under lockdown, victims of domestic violence are more likely to be trapped with their abusers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An early study conducted by my colleague, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lesscrime?lang=en&#34;&gt;Matt Ashby&lt;/a&gt;, examined &lt;a href=&#34;https://crimesciencejournal.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s40163-020-00117-6&#34;&gt;the effect of covid-19 on crime trends in 16 large cities in the United States&lt;/a&gt;. Matt&amp;rsquo;s study used a type of time series modelling technique called seasonal auto-regressive integrated moving average (SARIMA) to forecast the amount of crime that would be expected during the early months of 2020 and compared those forecasts with the trends actually observed since the pandemic in the US began. The study found:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;no significant changes in the frequency of serious assaults either in public or in residences (contrary to concerns among practitioners and policy makers), reductions in residential burglary in some (but not all) cities, little change in non-residential burglary (except in Minneapolis), decreases in thefts from vehicles in some cities, and diverging patterns of thefts of vehicles. It is noteworthy, however, that in no case were the patterns the same across all the cities under study (Ashby 2020, p 15).&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The somewhat modest effects of the pandemic on crime in these US cities could be explained by several factors. First, the study was conducted very early in the course of the pandemic, so it is possible that the full effects of the lockdowns could not be observed yet. It is quite possible that the effects of the pandemic on crime may take longer to become evident. On the other hand, crime in the US (and in the western world in general) has seen a &lt;a href=&#34;http://irep.ntu.ac.uk/id/eprint/26190/1/3652_Tseloni.pdf&#34;&gt;consistent crime drop&lt;/a&gt; over the last few decades, mostly due to the improvement of security. Thus, it is possible that small reductions may be lost in the noise expected in longitudinal crime patterns. As an example of the later point, consider that the lower bound of the confidence intervals around the SARIMA forecasts for some cities are at or near 0, meaning that even if a week had no crime during the pandemic, this would be within the expected range of variation. Lastly, as the study examined city-wide temporal patterns of crime, it did not explicitly took into account how much routine activities actually changed during the pandemic, nor how they may have changed within specific cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address some of these shortcomings, I&amp;rsquo;ve started a research project to examine the effect of the covid-19-related changes in routine activities on crime patterns in Mexico City. Mexico City represents an excellent opportunity to study the effect of covid-19 lockdowns on crime, as the city has an &lt;a href=&#34;https://datos.cdmx.gob.mx/pages/home/&#34;&gt;excellent open data initiative&lt;/a&gt; that regularly publishes incident-level crime data, as well as a data on urban mobility that can be reliably used to estimate changes in routine activities. Furthermore, there are few studies on crime patterns from an environmental criminology perspective outside of the English-speaking world, thus the study could advance the field by examining the relationship between routine activities and crime in a new setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details of the study can be found in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/4k9ds/&#34;&gt;project website&lt;/a&gt; at the Open Science Foundation. In a nutshell, I will first identify a suitable proxy measure to estimate the amount of activity outside homes (such as public transit passenger numbers, mobility apps trip queries, or amount of air pollution) before and after the social distancing restrictions imposed due to the Covid-19 epidemic. Then, I will examine if spatio-temporal crime patterns are associated with those of the proxy measures of routine activities. I plan on conducting city-wide analyses similar to those that Matt carried out, though I will also look at how crime patterns within the city may have changed in response to changes in mobility. For example, it may be particularly telling if crime decreases near public transit stations are correlated with changes in the amount of passengers that are using those stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this moment, the project is still in the planning phase. Data collection will begin by mid summer as data for May and June are published. It is expected that a first draft of the study will be completed by the end of the summer. For more information on this study, visit the &lt;a href=&#34;https://osf.io/4k9ds/&#34;&gt;project website&lt;/a&gt; or chat with me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/prestevez&#34;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p style=&#34;margin-left: 24pt; text-indent: -24.0pt;&#34;&gt;Ashby, M. P. J. (2020). Initial evidence on the relationship between the coronavirus pandemic and crime in the United States. &lt;i&gt;Crime Science&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;9&lt;/i&gt;(1), 6. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1186/s40163-020-00117-6&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/s40163-020-00117-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.ucl.ac.uk/jdi-lac/&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
the JDI Latin America and Caribbean Unit Blog&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.ucl.ac.uk/jdi-lac/2020/05/27/crime-and-covid-19-effect-of-changes-in-routine-activities-in-mexico-city/&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mexico: after a year in power, Andrés Manuel López Obrador is failing to contain violence</title>
      <link>/post/after-a-year-in-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/after-a-year-in-power/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When Mexico’s president, Andrés Manuel López Obrador, was sworn into office in December 2018 he promised swift action to stem the bloody crime wave that has ravaged the country &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/27/world/americas/27mexico.html&#34;&gt;in recent years&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with record-shattering homicide counts in &lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/2018/07/31/americas/mexico-homicides-2017-new-numbers/index.html&#34;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/23/mexico-crime-homicides-violence-up-report&#34;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt;, the new government promised drastic reductions in crime. López Obrador, known as AMLO, launched an &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-has-plans-to-make-his-country-safer-but-will-they-work-100441&#34;&gt;ambitious security plan&lt;/a&gt; focused on tackling the “root causes” of crime, ending the war against organised crime and overhauling &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-creates-yet-another-national-police-force-but-it-will-struggle-to-stem-the-bloody-crimewave-107320&#34;&gt;security institutions&lt;/a&gt;, such as the federal police.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the number of homicides remain at an all time high and the mishandling of repeated crises suggest that López Obrador’s government is overwhelmed by the deteriorating security situation in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since taking office, the president has repeatedly claimed that homicides &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.latimes.com/world/mexico-americas/la-fg-mexico-homicides-amlo-jorge-ramos-20190412-story.html&#34;&gt;started to drop since he came to power&lt;/a&gt;. But the government’s own data contradicted this. A closer inspection shows that the homicide rate has not decreased over the past year, although it has stopped its vertiginous increase &lt;a href=&#34;https://datos.nexos.com.mx/?p=1067&#34;&gt;for the first time in almost five years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;align-center zoomable&#34;&gt;
            &lt;a href=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=1000&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34; srcset=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=429&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=429&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=429&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=539&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=539&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/304696/original/file-20191202-67023-8d0xgp.png?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=539&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 2262w&#34; sizes=&#34;(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Homicides in Mexico.&lt;/span&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;attribution&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;license&#34;&gt;Author provided&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the news is hardly a cause for celebration. The current rate – which hovers between 80 and 100 homicides per day – is the highest the country has experienced since current records began in 1997. Sadly, the current lull is no guarantee that homicides will decrease in the future, and they may well increase again – as happened during the presidency of Enrique Peña Nieto between 2012 and 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hugs, not bullets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vowing to end the “war against organised crime”, the president opted for a non-confrontational approach to security, aiming to dissuade offenders and organised criminals through social policy, rather than through policing and criminal justice – a strategy the president summarises as “hugs, not bullets”. In early September, he urged criminals to &lt;a href=&#34;https://mexiconewsdaily.com/news/behave-and-think-of-your-mothers/&#34;&gt;behave and think of their mothers&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has sought to scale back the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/27/world/americas/mexican-militarys-high-kill-rate-raises-human-rights-fears.html&#34;&gt;lethality of its security forces&lt;/a&gt;, but several crises suggest that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/nov/05/mexicos-security-failure-grisly-cartel-shootout-shows-who-holds-the-power&#34;&gt;its light-touch approach is not working&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, 13 state police officers were executed in October by 30 cartel gunmen in an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/oct/15/mexico-police-officers-killed-cartel-ambush-michoacan&#34;&gt;ambush in Aguililla, Michoacán&lt;/a&gt;, a state in western Mexico. In response, the president offered no short-term strategy and instead blamed “social decomposition” in the region, vowing to continue pushing his economic and social policy – which has &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/09/world/americas/mexico-minster-urzua.html&#34;&gt;been criticised&lt;/a&gt; for being arbitrary and ill-defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same month, a more damming crisis erupted following the botched capture and subsequent &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/oct/18/el-chapo-son-ovidio-guzman-lopez-release-amlo&#34;&gt;release of Ovidio Guzmán&lt;/a&gt;, son of notorious drug trafficker, Joaquín “El Chapo” Guzmán, as cartel gunmen laid siege to Culiacán, capital of Sinaloa state, demanding the release of their leader. The president defended yielding to the cartel’s demands, arguing that not doing so would have led to a bloodbath. But critics &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/analysis/culiacan-shambles-security-plan-mexico/&#34;&gt;widely panned López Obrador&lt;/a&gt; for his government’s mishandling of the Culiacán crisis, noting that it would only embolden other criminal groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/_Wv1W0m4eOo&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three women and six children of a Mormon family &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/analysis/how-mexico-small-armies-commit-massacre/&#34;&gt;were then massacred in northern Mexico by a criminal group&lt;/a&gt; in November. As the victims held Mexican and American citizenship, the episode prompted the US president, Donald Trump, to consider designating Mexican criminal groups &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/nov/27/trump-mexico-drug-cartels-terrorists&#34;&gt;as foreign terrorist organisations&lt;/a&gt;, heightening tensions between the two countries. Trump ultimately &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-us-canada-50697635&#34;&gt;decided against it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;
      Read more:
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mormons-in-mexico-a-brief-history-of-polygamy-cartel-violence-and-faith-126493&#34;&gt;Mormons in Mexico: A brief history of polygamy, cartel violence and faith&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A lack of understanding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the root of the government’s failing security policies lie fundamental misunderstandings of Mexico’s criminal phenomenon. Specifically, López Obrador &lt;a href=&#34;https://politica.expansion.mx/presidencia/2019/08/01/amlo-calderon-violencia-organizaciones-lucha-anticorrupcion&#34;&gt;believes&lt;/a&gt; that violence is mainly caused by government security policy and economic strife. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0022002715587053?casa_token=1AJSvveCVkgAAAAA%3AuXN76Lo7Pbvzg-FmFldLgPmv8O_h68wQKX27n3GWBGxKUuTJOm9B497QsjM3NPYJ7HF_6ks6p0KoaRo&#34;&gt;evidence&lt;/a&gt; that certain security strategies &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/analysis/mexico-president-reprises-controversial-kingpin-strategy/&#34;&gt;can escalate cycles of violence&lt;/a&gt;. But organised crime violence is a deeply complex phenomenon caused by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/nathanielparishflannery/2019/11/22/how-can-mexico-defeat-organized-crime/#7e0ae3cac657&#34;&gt;a wide range of factors&lt;/a&gt; – such as international drug trends, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ft.com/content/69346c82-338c-11e9-bb0c-42459962a812&#34;&gt;competition between and within cartels&lt;/a&gt;, and the embeddedness of organised crime groups in local communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way in which the authorities intervene is certainly important, but it is not the only factor causing increases in violence. Furthermore, the absence of violence would not necessarily mean that organised crime groups are defeated, as it could signal a condition known as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/41391931&#34;&gt;“pax mafiosa”&lt;/a&gt;, in which criminal groups rule a territory in relative peace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming that criminal behaviour is caused by economic strife is a common, though too simplistic view of the problem. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cac.crim.cam.ac.uk/resou/sat&#34;&gt;Research suggests&lt;/a&gt; that criminal behaviour is far more complicated than that, noting that it emerges in certain places and times and not in others due to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-moral-ecology-of-extremism-a-systemic-perspective&#34;&gt;complex interaction&lt;/a&gt; of personal and contextual attributes. Of course, this does not mean that social policies should be abandoned, as they are important to improving welfare in general. But it’s unlikely that they will be enough to turn the tide of criminal violence currently rocking Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the government is to successfully tackle violence related to organised crime in Mexico, it must first take steps to acknowledge the inherent complexity of the problem. Rather than proposing a one-size-fits-all approach, specific policies need to be devised based on a nuanced understanding of the diverse criminal phenomena affecting specific places and their reality.&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation&#39;s page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/126460/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&#34; alt=&#34;The Conversation&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- End of code. If you don&#39;t see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexico-after-a-year-in-power-andres-manuel-lopez-obrador-is-failing-to-contain-violence-126460&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mexico’s new president creates yet another national police force – but it will struggle to stem the bloody crimewave</title>
      <link>/post/new-president-creates-new-police/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-president-creates-new-police/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mexico’s new president, Andrés Manuel López Obrador (known as AMLO), was sworn in on December 1, after a five month transition period following his &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/02/mexico-election-leftist-amlo-set-for-historic-landslide-victory&#34;&gt;landslide electoral victory&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faced with an unassailable crime wave that has ravaged the country since 2007 – when then-president Felipe Calderón (2006-2012) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/27/world/americas/27mexico.html&#34;&gt;declared an all-out war on organised crime&lt;/a&gt; – López Obrador outlined his security strategy shortly before taking office, after &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-has-plans-to-make-his-country-safer-but-will-they-work-100441&#34;&gt;months of speculation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;3HtKT&#34; class=&#34;tc-infographic-datawrapper&#34; src=&#34;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/3HtKT/1/&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border: none&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Against a background of nearly 30,000 intentional homicides a year (the worst rate in recent history), the plan contains some sensible – though vague – proposals, such as an overhaul of the prison system, and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/marijuana-in-mexico-how-to-legalise-it-effectively-fairly-and-safely-107856&#34;&gt;rethink of drug prohibition&lt;/a&gt;. But his plan has drawn &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/nov/21/president-elect-amlo-pledges-new-military-force-fight-crime-mexico&#34;&gt;intense criticism&lt;/a&gt; for proposing the creation of a new national guard under military control as the main tool to fight crime across the entire country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;
      Read more:
      &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/marijuana-in-mexico-how-to-legalise-it-effectively-fairly-and-safely-107856&#34;&gt;Marijuana in Mexico: how to legalise it effectively, fairly and safely&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The national guard would combine battalions from the army and navy, as well as the civilian Federal Police, into a new security force under the control of the Ministry of Defence. Furthermore, a recruitment drive aims to grow the fledgling force to 150,000 troops within three years. Though the new force will be nominally under civilian control, its training, discipline, values, hierarchy and daily operations will be under military command. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Boots on the ground&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the campaign, López Obrador promised to send the military back to the barracks. A decade of troops on the frontline of the drug wars has left a string of human rights abuses and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/27/world/americas/mexican-militarys-high-kill-rate-raises-human-rights-fears.html&#34;&gt;piling body count&lt;/a&gt;. So the announcement of a new national guard – which came shortly after the Supreme Court &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jurist.org/news/2018/11/mexico-supreme-court-rules-military-policing-law-unconstitutional/&#34;&gt;struck down&lt;/a&gt; a controversial law that permitted the use of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/as-the-cartels-grow-deadlier-should-the-mexican-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement-89134&#34;&gt;armed forces in policing duties&lt;/a&gt; – left many of his supporters in shock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the security plan would in effect dissolve the Federal Police – a civilian agency – and eschews any mention of improving the country’s weak municipal and state police agencies, the national guard is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/es/2018/11/28/opinion-lopez-obrador-guardia-nacional/&#34;&gt;seen by many&lt;/a&gt; as a permanent step towards military control of the security sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was extensively &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ipsnews.net/2018/11/president-elects-security-plan-disappoints-civil-society-mexico&#34;&gt;condemned by Mexican civil society&lt;/a&gt;, as well as by international organisations. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2018/11/mexico-el-plan-del-nuevo-gobierno-debe-enfocarse-en-retirar-las-fuerzas-armadas-de-funciones-de-seguridad-publica/&#34;&gt;Amnesty International&lt;/a&gt; said the proposal “essentially imitates the failed militarised security model [that] has allowed serious human rights violations to be committed by the armed forces”, while &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hrw.org/news/2018/11/16/mexico-military-policing-threatens-rights-0&#34;&gt;Human Rights Watch&lt;/a&gt; called it a “colossal mistake”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/157810194&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; title=&#34;vimeo video&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The trailer for Armed to the Teeth, a film about army brutality in Mexico.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, the proposed force is unlikely to be a panacea. On the one hand, it simply perpetuates the current security strategy that has so far failed to curb violence in the country. On the other, the national guard would still be too small to police a country as large and complex as Mexico, even assuming that it reaches its overly optimistic recruitment targets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The great paradox of police reform&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most worrying, however, is that the proposed national guard – the fourth new national police force to be created in as many presidencies – is a perfect example of what &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sup.org/books/title/?id=21512&#34;&gt;Daniel Sabet&lt;/a&gt; called “one of the great paradoxes of police reform in Mexico”. That “seemingly dramatic changes, such as dissolving one police force and creating an entirely new one, might in practice amount to very little reform of how policing is done”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To justify the national guard, López Obrador claims that there have been no improvements whatsoever in the quality of the police services in the past 12 years. This is not precisely true. While most police agencies are far from perfect, there have been notable improvements. The Federal Police has vastly improved its technical and human capabilities since 2006, and several state and municipal forces have become successful &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-43302244&#34;&gt;case&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/09/01/world/americas/mexico-violence-police.html?ref=nyt-es&amp;amp;mcid=nyt-es&amp;amp;subid=article&#34;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt; in their own right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;align-center &#34;&gt;
            &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34; srcset=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=658&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=658&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=658&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=827&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=827&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/248805/original/file-20181204-34154-1c9o9ln.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=827&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 2262w&#34; sizes=&#34;(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px&#34;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The Federal Police showcases its air capabilities.&lt;/span&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;attribution&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;source&#34; href=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/63/D%C3%ADa_del_Polic%C3%ADa._88_Aniversario_de_la_Polic%C3%ADa_Federal_%2827677338193%29.jpg&#34;&gt;Presidencia de la República Mexicana via Wikimedia Commons [CC BY 2.0]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&#34;license&#34; href=&#34;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#34;&gt;CC BY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that such improvements are sparse and have not yet made a notable improvement in security conditions across the country. Yet this is due to the complex nature of the criminal phenomenon, and the underwhelming commitment to institutional building by incoming politicians, who prefer flashy new policies over sticking to a plan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also true that corruption and abuse persist across police departments. But the armed forces are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/feb/10/mexico-drug-cartels-soldiers-military&#34;&gt;hardly immune to corruption&lt;/a&gt;. Studies have shown that the armed forces are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.animalpolitico.com/blogueros-blog-invitado/2018/11/15/ejercito-y-marina-bajo-la-lupa/&#34;&gt;more prone to commit torture and human rights abuses&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.politicaygobierno.cide.edu/index.php/pyg/article/view/1161&#34;&gt;more lethal&lt;/a&gt; than the police. Thus, it is unlikely that militarisation itself will lead to a more effective, incorruptible police force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remaking the security institutions every time a president takes power is incredibly counterproductive. Creating new institutions is costly and slow. Everything from the legislation (creating the national guard requires &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.proceso.com.mx/560409/morena-propone-modificar-13-articulos-de-la-constitucion-para-crear-la-guardia-nacional&#34;&gt;13 constitutional ammendments&lt;/a&gt; and a score of secondary rules) to the mundane (such as uniforms and the colours of patrol cars) must be defined and approved. This process tends to take much longer than anticipated, wasting resources at the expense of actual police work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better alternative would focus on a long-term commitment to improving Mexico’s fledgling civilian police agencies. Corruption is an inherent risk of all police agencies, yet there is evidence that corrupted police agencies &lt;a href=&#34;http://eprints.lse.ac.uk/68126/1/Newburn_literature-review%201.pdf&#34;&gt;can be successfully reformed&lt;/a&gt;. By creating a new force, rather than solving Mexico’s security crisis, López Obrador will be setting the country back in its long and arduous road towards capable policing.&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation&#39;s page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/107320/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&#34; alt=&#34;The Conversation&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- End of code. If you don&#39;t see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-creates-yet-another-national-police-force-but-it-will-struggle-to-stem-the-bloody-crimewave-107320&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mexico’s new president has plans to make his country safer – but will they work?</title>
      <link>/post/new-president-has-plans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/new-president-has-plans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mexican voters upended their country’s political establishment this summer when they elected Andres Manuel López Obrador – the left-wing former mayor of Mexico City known as AMLO – by an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/02/mexico-election-leftist-amlo-set-for-historic-landslide-victory&#34;&gt;overwhelming margin&lt;/a&gt;. His impressive victory owed a lot to his personal charisma and populist rhetoric, but it also reflected the public’s weariness with Mexico’s current state of affairs – and in particular, with criminal violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long a problem for Mexico, deadly violence is now at an all time high. There were &lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/2018/07/31/americas/mexico-homicides-2017-new-numbers/index.html&#34;&gt;more than 31,000 murders in 2017&lt;/a&gt;, the highest number on record, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jul/23/mexico-crime-homicides-violence-up-report&#34;&gt;this year is shaping up to be even deadlier&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;López Obrador’s term begins on December 1, but his incoming government has already &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AlfonsoDurazo/status/1028131486678044672&#34;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to reduce violent crime by between 30-50% within three years, and to bring crime rates in line with those in OECD countries &lt;a href=&#34;http://uk.businessinsider.com/oecd-homicide-rates-chart-2015-6&#34;&gt;within six years&lt;/a&gt;. To achieve this, it has come up with three strategies: tackling the “root causes” of crime through social policy, ending the war against organised crime, and restructuring security institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the central ideas behind López Obrador’s approach to security is that when it comes to fighting crime, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eleconomista.com.mx/politica/El-reto-es-hallar-las-personas-indicadas-para-hacer-la-tarea-Alfonso-Durazo-20180728-0001.html&#34;&gt;the best policy is social policy&lt;/a&gt;. But muddling social policy with crime policy is troublesome; rather than lifting people out of criminogenic conditions, it can simply spawn a welter of social programmes that have little bearing on crime at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what happened during the tenure of the outgoing administration, when every proposal from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cidob.org/en/articulos/revista_cidob_d_afers_internacionals/116/the_effects_of_prevention_of_crime_and_violence_policy_in_mexico&#34;&gt;cooking lessons to handing out free glasses to schoolchildren&lt;/a&gt; was held up as a worthwhile crime prevention initiative. This sort of policymaking neglects the fact that the police can actually be &lt;a href=&#34;http://whatworks.college.police.uk/toolkit/Pages/Toolkit.aspx&#34;&gt;very effective at preventing crime&lt;/a&gt; in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AMLO clearly sees things differently. He plans to roll out an extensive scholarship programme aimed at preventing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://verne.elpais.com/verne/2018/02/02/mexico/1517594700_019834.html&#34;&gt;7m young people not in education, employment or training&lt;/a&gt; from joining criminal gangs, even though there is no consistent evidence showing that youth unemployment and poverty are the main drivers of involvement in organised crime. Though scant research on this topic has been conducted in Mexico itself, evidence from the UK has shown the opposite: as youth unemployment and poverty has increased, the amount of crime committed by this age group has actually &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/is-there-a-link-between-youth-poverty-and-crime-the-answers-may-surprise-you-50097&#34;&gt;decreased&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Beyond the drug war&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a different front, the incoming government has correctly identified the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/dec/26/mexico-maelstrom-how-the-drug-violence-got-so-bad&#34;&gt;decade-long war on organised crime&lt;/a&gt; as one of the main drivers of violence. But while it has proposed a three-pronged plan to bring about peace, it is unlikely that this is achievable in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, AMLO and his team have proposed implementing a process of transitional justice to break the cycle of violence, including a controversial &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/amnesty-for-drug-traffickers-thats-one-mexican-presidential-candidates-pitch-to-voters-96063&#34;&gt;amnesty for low-level drug-traffickers&lt;/a&gt;. There is still much uncertainty as to how this would be implemented, but it remains unclear whether it would actually help end violence in Mexico, since these mechanisms were designed to manage the aftermath of political and ethnic conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, with a growing global consensus that the current &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/apr/02/un-war-on-drugs-failure-prohibition-united-nations&#34;&gt;drug prohibition regime has failed&lt;/a&gt;, the new government plans to legalise cannabis and the cultivation of opium poppies. However, wholesale legalisation of cannabis has never been attempted in a country as large and complex – and as fraught with poor institutions – as Mexico. That means it may be years before legalisation is implemented, as the necessary regulatory frameworks and institutions will have to be established first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, legalisation in Mexico would create more opportunities for smuggling drugs into the US – potentially a boon for some organised crime groups, and potentially a serious risk to an already troubled relationship with Washington.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the new government has pledged to train enough police officers to &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/as-the-cartels-grow-deadlier-should-the-mexican-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement-89134&#34;&gt;remove the armed forces&lt;/a&gt; from the fight against organised crime in three years. But this plan is based on a highly optimistic estimate of the state’s capacity to recruit and train new police officers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 2015 and 2016, there were &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vox.com/2018/8/15/17690420/mexico-president-amlo-drug-war-cartels-violence-legalization&#34;&gt;133,000 soldiers involved in the fight against organised crime&lt;/a&gt;; replacing them would require at least 50,000 new elite federal police officers. President Calderón (2006-2012) took six years to recruit 20,000 federal police officers. His successor, Peña Nieto, promised a 50,000-strong National Gendarmerie, but ultimately delivered a force of fewer than 5,000. It’s highly unlikely that the new government will be able to perform any better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reinventing the police&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incoming government has also hinted at yet another redesign of Mexico’s security institutions. Though they have &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.animalpolitico.com/2018/07/guardia-nacional-amlo-seguridad/&#34;&gt;dropped a plan&lt;/a&gt; to create a “National Guard” incorporating the army and the police, AMLO plans to recreate the Federal Security Ministry (dissolved by the outgoing president, Enrique Peña Nieto), to form a new police force charged with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2018-07-13/amlo-s-top-cop-no-longer-sees-new-border-police-force-in-mexico&#34;&gt;protecting tourist destinations&lt;/a&gt;, and to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cfr.org/blog/coming-us-mexico-blow&#34;&gt;replace the country’s intelligence agency&lt;/a&gt; with an entirely new body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These reforms are likely to take much longer than anticipated, wasting precious resources that could otherwise be spent on actual police work. And even if they’re implemented swiftly, they are &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/analysis/mexico-needlessly-plans-to-alter-justice-agency/&#34;&gt;unlikely to directly improve the security situation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mexico is simply too vast and too diverse for centralised control of security policy to work. The federal government does not and will not have the resources to properly deal with most of its crime problems. A better approach would be to delegate responsibility to state and local governments, using federal policy to induce improvements in local policing. Security institutions require continuity and time to mature; small, incremental improvements to their operations are a better bet than wholesale redesign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The security situation in Mexico remains dire, and it’s likely to remain that way for some time. Social policy can help reduce poverty and improve welfare, but it’s no substitute for intelligent, evidence-based crime prevention delivered by a well-trained local police. Removing the army from the streets without capable police officers to replace them could strengthen organised crime groups and make the situation worse.&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation&#39;s page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/100441/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&#34; alt=&#34;The Conversation&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- End of code. If you don&#39;t see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/mexicos-new-president-has-plans-to-make-his-country-safer-but-will-they-work-100441&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flawed Measurements of Organised Crime Activities</title>
      <link>/post/flawed-measurements-extortion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/flawed-measurements-extortion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Extortion against businesses is one of the main security challenges
facing the Mexican government today. Statistics from crimes reported to
the police show that extortion has increased dramatically since the
country was plunged into a decade-long ‘war’ against organised crime,
rising by about &lt;a href=&#34;http://secretariadoejecutivo.gob.mx/docs/pdfs/cifras%20de%20homicidio%20doloso%20secuestro%20etc/HDSECEXTRV_122017.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;81% in the past 10
years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, given the risk of reprisals entailed by reporting extortion
incidents to the authorities, estimates from reported crimes rarely
provide reliable measurements of extortion incidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To mitigate this shortcoming, Mexico’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inegi.org.mx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;national statistics agency
(INEGI)&lt;/a&gt; conducts regular victimisation surveys
that measure extortion, among other crimes. Estimates from surveys
conducted with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inegi.org.mx/saladeprensa/boletines/2017/envipe/envipe2017_09.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;households
(ENVIPE)&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.beta.inegi.org.mx/contenidos/proyectos/encestablecimientos/especiales/enve/2016/doc/enve_2016_presentacion_ejecutiva.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;businesses
(ENVE)&lt;/a&gt;,
suggest that extortion is, indeed, a widespread problem: it is the
second most common crime against households, and the third most common
crime against businesses. In the year of the latest available figures
(2016 for the household survey, and 2015 for the commercial survey),
there were an estimated 7.5 million incidents of extortion against
households (89 extortions per 1,000 people), and 650,000 incidents of
extortion against businesses (146 extortions per 1,000 businesses).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extortion has important economic, political and social implications.
First, widespread extortion in the countryside has been linked to
dramatic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jornada.unam.mx/2013/07/20/opinion/017a2pol&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;increases in the prices of food
staples&lt;/a&gt;, while
extortion in general is often portrayed as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-13120598&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;generalised burden on the
economy&lt;/a&gt; by imposing an
informal tax on many businesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jstor.org/stable/23526915&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;rise of the &lt;em&gt;fuerzas de autodefensa&lt;/em&gt; (self-defence
forces)&lt;/a&gt; during the first year of
President Peña Nieto’s term shows how grave the political implications
of extortion can be. Faced with rampant extortion and violence inflicted
by organised crime, civilian groups in many rural areas of the country
set up armed paramilitary brigades to fight organised crime and expel
what they saw as ineffectual and corrupt local governments—though some
&lt;em&gt;autodefensas&lt;/em&gt; eventually &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.insightcrime.org/news/brief/mexico-vigilantes-protection-fees-echo-colombias-paramilitaries/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;turned
into&lt;/a&gt;
extortive criminal groups themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August 2011, a casino in Monterrey was set ablaze for refusing to
acquiesce to extortion demands&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, extortion has been linked to some of the deadliest incidents of
violence against Mexican society. In August 2011, a casino in
Monterrey—a city in northern Mexico—was &lt;a href=&#34;http://articles.latimes.com/2011/aug/29/world/la-fg-mexico-casino-arrests-20110830&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;set
ablaze&lt;/a&gt;
for refusing to acquiesce to extortion demands. The incident, which
killed 52 patrons of the establishment, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-14693074&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;left the country
reeling&lt;/a&gt;,
prompting then-President Calderón to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2011/aug/26/52-die-arson-mexico-casino&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;declare three days of national
mourning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such dramatic episodes, in conjunction with the dispiriting estimates of
extortion incidence produced by INEGI, have fuelled the belief that
extortion is inescapable. Based on academic work on extortion rackets,
such as Diego Gambetta’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Sicilian-Mafia-Business-Private-Protection/dp/0674807421&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;1993
study&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/225889684_The_Paradoxes_of_Organized_Crime&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Letizia Paoli’s 2002
study&lt;/a&gt;
on the Italian mafia, scholars have suggested that Mexico’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://securitypraxis.eu/mexico-narcoviolence-mafia-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;transition
to democracy and endemic
corruption&lt;/a&gt;
generated power vacuums that have been exploited by the country’s
criminal groups—commonly known as ‘cartels’—prompting them to shift
their business models from trafficking drugs from Mexico to the US, into
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nbcnews.com/id/32437386/ns/world_news-americas/t/mexico-cartels-turning-full-scale-mafias/#.WnXv6iOcaRs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mafia-style extortion
rackets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This interpretation feeds into a narrative that paints Mexico as a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/01/07/world/americas/mexico-state-corruption.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;failed
state&lt;/a&gt;,
where organised crime violence has &lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/a-report-says-that-mexico-is-the-second-deadliest-conflict-zone-in-the-world-its-just-not-true-77898&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;purportedly
escalated&lt;/a&gt;
beyond what is seen in war-torn countries. Such an approach leaves few
policy options to deal with extortion specifically, suggesting instead
policies to root out organised crime by slowly reclaiming the state’s
control of social and physical spheres ceded to the cartels by direct
confrontation, prosecution and by building effective institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-two-flavours-of-extortion&#34;&gt;The Two Flavours of Extortion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A distinction often missed when discussing the nature and implications
of the extortion phenomenon in Mexico is that it encompasses two
distinct crime types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, there is ‘telephone extortion’, which refers to
attempts to extract money (or other benefits) from victims through
threats made remotely via telephone calls. In general, victims are
cold-called by assailants who either offer a non-existent reward (a form
of advanced-fee scam), claim to have kidnapped a family member (‘virtual
kidnapping’), or claim to be a member of an organised crime group and
threaten to carry out severe punishments if victims do not comply with
stated demands. It is believed that most victims are selected randomly,
though some are targeted using information gleaned from data breaches,
social media, or from other unrelated telemarketing calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, ‘in-person extortion’ refers to attempts to extract
money (or other benefits) by directly threatening the victim in person.
In these incidents, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.inegi.org.mx/rde/2013/05/09/crime-against-the-private-sector-in-latin-america-existing-data-and-future-orientations-to-analyse-the-victimization-of-businesses/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;assailants
threaten&lt;/a&gt;
a business or household with damage, assault, death or other harms if
they refuse to pay a fee, and may also involve offers to protect the
victim from other criminal groups. When such in-person extortion
attempts happen regularly, the crime is called &lt;em&gt;cobro de piso&lt;/em&gt;, which is
roughly translated as a ‘fee for the floor’ where businesses operate,
although this distinction is not consistently used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is widely acknowledged that many telephone extortions originate
from prisons, and that most victims face little danger if they ignore
the threats&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas in-person extortion fits with the modus operandi of extortion
racketeering traditionally associated with the mafia and other organised
crime groups, telephone extortion is better described as a type of scam,
more akin to email spam than to extortion racketeering. Furthermore, it
is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chron.com/news/nation-world/article/Mexico-extortion-racket-growing-from-behind-bars-1835082.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;widely
acknowledged&lt;/a&gt;
that many telephone extortions originate from prisons, and that most
victims face little danger if they ignore the threats. Preliminary
findings from my ongoing research support this notion, as the crimes
vary dramatically in terms of the harms and risks posed to victims. When
compared to telephone extortion incidents, in-person extortions are 8.5
times more likely to lead to victim acquiescence with extortionists’
demands, and 5.4 times more likely to involve reprisals for refusing to
acquiesce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These distinctions strongly suggest that the crimes ought to be
considered as separate offence classes. Despite this, figures from
reported crime statistics and victimisation survey estimates routinely
report measurements that aggregate both telephone and in-person
extortions, misrepresenting the true nature and extent of the phenomena.
Specifically, lumping both crime types severely overestimates the
gravity of the extortion phenomenon, as telephone extortion is far more
common than in-person extortion (telephone extortions comprise around
94% of all extortion incidents against households, and 88% of extortions
against businesses). Thus, the widespread prevalence and incidence of
extortion does not accurately reflect the specific harms and risks of
extortion, by making the situation appear far worse than it actually is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-upshot&#34;&gt;The Upshot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does not imply that telephone extortion is not a problem that needs
to be dealt with. The fact that many victims believe the mostly empty
threats behind telephone extortion is a symptom of an environment where
fear of crime is endemic. Yet, there is little evidence that telephone
extortions are linked to extortion rackets controlled by organised crime
groups. Telephone extortionists are not spatially bound to specific
territories, nor do they impose alternative governance structures. Thus
they cannot be directly interpreted as evidence of state failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A flawed measurement of organised criminal activity can feed
misleading narratives&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the comparatively smaller prevalence and incidence of
in-person extortions suggest that the far graver problem of extortion
racketeering is not as widespread in Mexico and may instead be limited
to a small number of places, even after accounting for measurement
errors. Nonetheless, further research that looks at the phenomenon at
the local scale is needed to determine its nature and extent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this does not mean that Mexico does not have an organised
crime problem, nor that democratic governance need not improve. However,
it does highlight how a flawed measurement of organised criminal
activity can feed misleading narratives. One of the most crucial aspects
of public policy formulation is defining the problem under scrutiny,
something especially relevant when dealing with organised crime—a
phenomenon that resists easy definitions. Thus, before any plausible
policy interventions to counter extortion in Mexico can be devised, it
is necessary to revise how the phenomenon itself is defined and
measured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://shoc.rusi.org/the-informer&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Informer&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://shoc.rusi.org/informer/flawed-measurements-organised-crime-activities-case-extortion-mexico&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>As the cartels grow deadlier, should the Mexican military be involved in law enforcement?</title>
      <link>/post/should-the-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/should-the-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement/</guid>
      <description>  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/199203/original/file-20171214-27593-10frerr.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;figcaption&gt;
        Boots on the ground.
        &lt;span class=&#34;attribution&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;source&#34; href=&#34;https://www.shutterstock.com/download/confirm/609862967?src=D_gW8H_zgs3FQHVU8cTjyQ-1-0&amp;size=medium_jpg&#34;&gt;Shutterstock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the main mission of the Mexican Armed Forces (army, air force and navy) is to safeguard national security, Mexico is faced with very few direct foreign threats. Consequently, the armed forces instead focus most of their attention on internal threats: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/live/2017/sep/21/mexico-earthquake-search-for-survivors-live-frida-sofia-updates&#34;&gt;emergency response to natural disasters&lt;/a&gt;, and temporary operations for countering organised crime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Successive Mexican presidents have continuously relied on the well-armed and highly respected armed forces to combat the large and powerful organised crime groups (colloquially known as “cartels”) that dominate the Latin American drug trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have done it for two reasons. On the one hand, local and state police forces have been neglected for decades and have been unable to cope with the corruptive influence of criminal groups. On the other, federal police forces have been too weak and small to counter the national presence of powerful cartels. So when faced with a rising death toll and increasingly violent organised crime groups, presidents have had few alternatives but to turn to the military.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div data-react-class=&#34;Tweet&#34; data-react-props=&#34;{&amp;quot;tweetId&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;940656527685271552&amp;quot;}&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until a decade ago, these interventions were rather sporadic. The most dramatic upsurge came about in 2006, when then-president Felipe Calderón (2006-2012) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/27/world/americas/27mexico.html&#34;&gt;declared an all-out war on organised crime&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the decade-long strategy was successful in breaking apart the main organised crime groups, violence induced by splinter groups and new actors has not abated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strategy has plunged the country into an ongoing conflict that has cost thousands of lives. Furthermore, it has also provoked countless human rights violations by the security forces (including the military) in the form of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/campaigns/2015/10/stop-torture-mexico/&#34;&gt;torture&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=20143&#34;&gt;extrajudicial killings&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hrw.org/news/2013/02/20/mexico-crisis-enforced-disappearances&#34;&gt;forced disappearances&lt;/a&gt;, and has led to an explosion in criminality in both &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.animalpolitico.com/2012/10/aumenta-delincuencia-comun/&#34;&gt;petty&lt;/a&gt; and serious crime, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/the_americas/kidnappings-in-mexico-surge-to-the-highest-number-on-record/2014/08/15/3f8ee2d2-1e6e-11e4-82f9-2cd6fa8da5c4_story.html?utm_term=.c2a58b74639e&#34;&gt;kidnapping&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.huffingtonpost.com/fundacion-mepi/extortion-by-fire-more-me_b_3202869.html&#34;&gt;extortion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;QJnd8&#34; class=&#34;tc-infographic-datawrapper&#34; src=&#34;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/QJnd8/1/&#34; height=&#34;400px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; style=&#34;border: none&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;President Peña Nieto (in office since 2012) has sought to scale back the focus of the Calderón government’s war on organised crime. This led to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/news/special-report/21566774-after-five-years-soaring-murder-rates-killings-have-last-begun-level&#34;&gt;an illusory lull in homicide trends&lt;/a&gt; for the first couple of years of his term, only for violence to return with a vengeance: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/entry/mexico-october-deadliest-month_us_5a158a7ee4b09650540e9189&#34;&gt;October 2017 was Mexico’s deadliest month on record&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around the tenth anniversary of the war on organised crime, Mexico’s secretary of defence &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eluniversal.com.mx/articulo/nacion/seguridad/2016/12/5/cienfuegos-no-confundir-seguridad-interior-con-seguridad-publica&#34;&gt;complained&lt;/a&gt; about the lack of a proper legal framework for the involvement of the armed forces in “matters of internal security”, including the fight against organised crime. Such criticism was echoing a 2012 statement by a minister of the Supreme Court, who &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.animalpolitico.com/2012/08/el-ejercito-no-esta-para-cumplir-funciones-de-seguridad-publica-cossio-integro/&#34;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; that the constitution did not empower the army to take on roles attributed to civil law enforcement agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Internal Security Law&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fill this legal vacuum, legislators proposed an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.senado.gob.mx/sgsp/gaceta/63/3/2017-12-05-1/assets/documentos/Minuta_Ley_Seguridad_Interior.pdf&#34;&gt;Internal Security Law&lt;/a&gt;, approved on November 30 by the Chamber of Deputies (Mexico’s lower house of congress), with support from the governing PRI party and a few PAN deputies (the largest opposition party). The bill set to now be debated (and probably approved) by the Senate seeks to regulate the involvement of the armed forces in “threats to internal security”. Such interventions would have to be requested by state governments, or could be initiated by the president if the threats are deemed to be urgent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;align-center &#34;&gt;
            &lt;img alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;fit=clip&#34; srcset=&#34;https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=398&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=398&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=600&amp;amp;h=398&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=45&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=501&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=30&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=501&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/199202/original/file-20171214-27580-14tip4d.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;amp;q=15&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;w=754&amp;amp;h=501&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;dpr=3 2262w&#34; sizes=&#34;(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px&#34;&gt;
            &lt;figcaption&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The police are struggling to contain a wave of violent crime.&lt;/span&gt;
              &lt;span class=&#34;attribution&#34;&gt;&lt;a class=&#34;source&#34; href=&#34;https://www.shutterstock.com/image-photo/veracruz-mexico-january-192015antidrug-special-foreces-336562550?src=D_gW8H_zgs3FQHVU8cTjyQ-1-2&#34;&gt;Shutterstock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;/figcaption&gt;
          &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proponents of the law note that such “actions of internal security” are never supposed to substitute local law enforcement; are bound to respect human rights; are to be deployed only against specific threats for a limited time (though subject to extensions); are explicitly forbidden to be used against peaceful social and political protests; and should involve the military only if the Federal Police cannot deal with the threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the proposed law has been met with wide opposition from civil society organisations, academics, and international organisations such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ohchr.org/EN/NewsEvents/Pages/DisplayNews.aspx?NewsID=22492&amp;amp;LangID=E&#34;&gt;United Nations Office of the High Commissioner for Human Rights&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hrw.org/news/2017/12/07/mexico-reject-internal-security-law&#34;&gt;Human Rights Watch&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://amnistia.org.mx/contenido/declaracion-ai-ley-de-seguridad-interior/&#34;&gt;Amnesty International&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics claim that given the country’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2017/nov/07/mexican-military-human-rights-abuses-war-on-drugs-report&#34;&gt;poor track record&lt;/a&gt; in punishing human rights abuses by the military, institutionalising their role in law enforcement could lead to more abuse. Furthermore, they argue that the vague definition of “threats to internal security” gives too much discretion to the president, prompting fears that the military might be deployed as a tool of political repression. They also complain that the law rolls back accountability and transparency, as all information related to such interventions would be automatically classified as state secrets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It’s about trust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that there is a legal void regarding the involvement of the armed forces in internal threats. Such participation of the military in civilian life is not exclusive to Mexico. Liberal democracies increasingly resort to the military &lt;a href=&#34;http://euromil.org/the-use-of-military-forces-for-internal-security-tasks/&#34;&gt;in support of internal security missions&lt;/a&gt;, including in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-16195861&#34;&gt;the UK&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/apr/15/paris-attacks-operation-sentinelle-soldiers-patrolling-streets-france-safer&#34;&gt;France&lt;/a&gt;, for example. The question is how, and to what extent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed law does attempt to regulate such involvement in principle, however it does little more than state in law what already takes place in practice. Not surprisingly, this raises legitimate fears that it will only lead to a perpetuation of the status quo at the expense of developing capable local civil law enforcement institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A truly beneficial law on internal security, if any, would go to greater lengths to curb the executive’s use of the armed forces to deal with internal security problems, for example by mandating stricter mechanisms for oversight (including legislative and judicial control) and by defaulting the interventions at their most restrictive setting, rather than leaving their terms to executive discretion.&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation&#39;s page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/89134/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&#34; alt=&#34;The Conversation&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- End of code. If you don&#39;t see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/as-the-cartels-grow-deadlier-should-the-mexican-military-be-involved-in-law-enforcement-89134&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A report says that Mexico is the second-deadliest conflict zone in the world – it’s just not true</title>
      <link>/post/a-report-says-mexico/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/a-report-says-mexico/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;According to a report published in early May, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/politics/articles/2017-05-09/mexico-now-world-s-deadliest-conflict-zone-after-syria-survey&#34;&gt;Mexico has become&lt;/a&gt; the second-deadliest conflict zone in the world in 2016. The claim came from a press release for the 2017 edition of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iiss.org/en/publications/acs/by%20year/armed-conflict-survey-2017-8efc&#34;&gt;Armed Conflict Survey (ACS)&lt;/a&gt; by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iiss.org/en&#34;&gt;International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS)&lt;/a&gt;, a London-based think tank. And a media frenzy followed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IISS press release &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iiss.org/-/media//documents/publications/acs/acs%202017/acs-2017-press-notice.pdf?la=en&#34;&gt;stated&lt;/a&gt; that the 23,000 deaths in 2016 that it attributes to Mexico’s struggle against organised crime, came second to the 50,000 fatalities caused by Syria’s civil war. They said this was higher than those caused by conflicts in the rest of the countries covered by the survey, including Iraq, Afghanistan, Yemen, and the so-called “Northern Triangle” of El Salvador, Honduras and Guatemala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The claim was shared extensively, including via a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/DRUDGE_REPORT/status/862028109394006016&#34;&gt;retweet&lt;/a&gt; by US president Donald Trump. But it drew &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gob.mx/sre/prensa/comunicado-conjunto-106478&#34;&gt;swift criticism from Mexico’s government&lt;/a&gt;, which argued, among other things, that Mexico’s organised crime-related violence is not comparable to armed conflicts in Syria or Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, IISS published a blog post outlining &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iiss.org/en/iiss%20voices/blogsections/iiss-voices-2017-adeb/may-8636/is-mexico-really-in-a-state-of-conflict-42f3&#34;&gt;why it thinks Mexico is in a state of conflict&lt;/a&gt;, including  Mexico’s own characterisation of criminal groups as an existential threat under the previous government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.ucl.ac.uk/organised-crime/2017/05/11/is-mexico-really-the-second-deadliest-conflict-zone-in-the-world/&#34;&gt;argue&lt;/a&gt; that the comparison placing Mexico as the second-deadliest conflict zone is fallacious for two main reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bushel of apples, truckload of oranges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the comparison did not take into account the vastly different sizes of the countries in the study. Mexico’s population (127m) is larger than the most recent population figures for Syria, Iraq, Afghanistan and Yemen combined (114.2m). All else being equal, it is expected that countries with larger populations will have more fatalities or homicides in absolute terms. For example, there where almost twice as many homicides in the US (12,000) as there were fatalities in Yemen (7,000), but this is because the US has a population that is 12 times bigger than Yemen’s, not because it is deadlier than Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To account for different population sizes in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.insightcrime.org/news-analysis/insight-crime-2016-homicide-round-up&#34;&gt;cross-national comparisons&lt;/a&gt;, mortality and homicide figures are usually expressed as incidents per 100,000 people. This captures the probability that individuals in a given country face of being killed, and so are a better measure than absolute figures. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As seen in the graph below, once population sizes are taken into account, the probability of being killed in Mexico was much lower than in the rest of the countries in the ACS top five or in the Northern Triangle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&#34;datawrapper-chart-o7NOh&#34; src=&#34;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/o7NOh/2/&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34; allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34; webkitallowfullscreen=&#34;webkitallowfullscreen&#34; mozallowfullscreen=&#34;mozallowfullscreen&#34; oallowfullscreen=&#34;oallowfullscreen&#34; msallowfullscreen=&#34;msallowfullscreen&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the figures being compared are not measuring the same phenomenon. In the report, fatalities in Mexico and Central America refer to the total amount of intentional homicides, while in the rest of the countries in the study, they refer to deaths directly caused by armed conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is true that intentional homicides are sometimes used as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://justiceinmexico.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/03/2017_DrugViolenceinMexico.pdf&#34;&gt;proxy measurement of organised crime activity in Mexico&lt;/a&gt; – something I am exploring in my ongoing research. However, that does not mean that it is appropriate to uncritically compare the absolute number of homicides in Mexico to conflict-related fatalities in other countries. That would suggest that all intentional homicides in Mexico – &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economist.com/news/americas/21721973-gangs-get-smaller-and-diversify-why-murder-mexico-rising-again&#34;&gt;high as they may be&lt;/a&gt; – can be attributed to organised crime violence, which is far from the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Beware distortions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous editions of the ACS in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iiss.org/en/about%20us/press%20room/press%20releases/press%20releases/archive/2015-4fe9/may-6219/armed-conflict-survey-2015-press-statement-a0be&#34;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.iiss.org/en/about%20us/press%20room/press%20releases/press%20releases/archive/2016-3b31/may-2fc6/acs-2016-press-release-b853&#34;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt; also included Mexico and reported similarly high levels of fatalities. But the level of coverage of the 2017 report reflects a vastly different global public agenda. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/news/ryan-lizza/donald-trump-blows-up-the-u-s-mexico-relationship&#34;&gt;Mexico-US relations at a new low&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/politics/nafta-renegotiation-process/?utm_term=.3a3d3b64353c&#34;&gt;looming renegotiation of the North American Free Trade Agreement&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cbsnews.com/news/will-trump-ever-get-his-border-wall/&#34;&gt;the promise of a new physical wall between the two countries&lt;/a&gt;, it is not surprising that IISS’s press statement landed front and centre in the international news media – even if such comparisons are not the main focus of the ACS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalists undeniably “&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/journalists-must-get-better-at-science-43320&#34;&gt;have to get better at reporting science&lt;/a&gt;”. But academics and those involved in research – especially in controversial issues such as crime and security – also need to exercise care when publicising their findings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a tension between the efforts to publicise research by highlighting headline-grabbing findings, and the risk of having such findings overhyped and misrepresented, or even spun into a deliberate political agenda, as the right-wing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.breitbart.com/big-government/2017/05/11/report-gun-controlled-mexico-second-syria-armed-conflict-violence/&#34;&gt;Breitbart News&lt;/a&gt; did with the IISS announcement. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academics and think tanks may not have much control over how their findings are reported by the media once they are released to the public. So it is imperative to take extra care when communicating them to the press, and setting out clearly what are the limitations of the findings, as well as the generalisations that can accurately be drawn from them.&lt;!-- Below is The Conversation&#39;s page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://counter.theconversation.com/content/77898/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic&#34; alt=&#34;The Conversation&#34; width=&#34;1&#34; height=&#34;1&#34; style=&#34;border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important; text-shadow: none !important&#34; /&gt;&lt;!-- End of code. If you don&#39;t see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
This article was originally published in
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
The Conversation&lt;/a&gt;. Read the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://theconversation.com/a-report-says-that-mexico-is-the-second-deadliest-conflict-zone-in-the-world-its-just-not-true-77898&#34; target=&#34;new&#34;&gt;
 original article&lt;/a&gt;.
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
